<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mireia Valle | </title>
    <link>/authors/mireia-valle/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/mireia-valle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Mireia Valle</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Mireia Valle</title>
      <link>/authors/mireia-valle/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future Sea</title>
      <link>/project/futuresea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/futuresea/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;research-objectives&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Research objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FutureSea’s overarching objective is to envision the future of seascapes under climate change, using a social-ecological seascape (SES) system approach, scaling down from a global ecological analysis to more socially relevant local scales that also consider distant impacts of local decision-making. To do so we have defined an integration methodology (Figure 1), which will start developing an ecological trait-based approach to explain the responses of marine biodiversity to global drivers of marine ecosystem change and the effects of biodiversity on marine ES; and will finalize with a participatory scenario modeling approach to envision sustainability transition pathways at relevant local policy level. This would lead to new insights for adaptive ecosystem management towards better marine spatial planning aiming at fostering resilient SES systems. The research objective will be approached from an interdisciplinary sustainable science perspective by combining cutting-edge ecological research on marine functional traits and climate change; and the study of complex social-ecological systems through a participatory approach, with emphasis on scenario analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;activities&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Activities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;a trait-based approach at global scale where mapping and projections of marine biodiversity functional responses to climate change will be performed;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;linking of key biodiversity-related ecosystem functions to ES,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;an assessment of marine protected areas (MPAs) effectiveness given socio-ecological contexts and spillover effects;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;deriving lessons relevant for the Basque Country Fishing Guild of Bizkaia to develop participatory scenarios in order to provide policy relevant information related to the implementation of adaptive ecosystem-based fishery management; and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;a cross-scale interdisciplinary synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Resilient Fisheries</title>
      <link>/project/climate-resilient-fisheries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/climate-resilient-fisheries/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;goals&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goals:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provide consensus view of the key features of climate-resilient fisheries and examples of application of these features in fishery management systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Develop a decision support tool to help managers identify resilience capacity and needs, and to provide guidance on approaches to enhance resilience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work with leaders of fishery management organizations to tailor results and products for global, national, and regional application in a variety of fisheries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rocky Reef Ecosystems</title>
      <link>/project/rockyreedecosystems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/rockyreedecosystems/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;activities&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Activities:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Integral monitoring of marine benthic invertebrates (corals and echinoderms): mapping and modellinh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Growth rate assessment of two reef-building coral species &lt;em&gt;Pocillopora damicornis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pocillopora capitata&lt;/em&gt; based on field experiments&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Wrangling and Visualization</title>
      <link>/post/datawrangling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/datawrangling/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/kePrint/kePrint.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;attach-packages-read-in-and-explore-the-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attach packages, read in and explore the data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attach (load) packages with &lt;code&gt;library()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read in NOAA Commercial Fisheries Landing data (1950 - 2017) Accessed from: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.st.nmfs.noaa.gov/commercial-fisheries/commercial-landings/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.st.nmfs.noaa.gov/commercial-fisheries/commercial-landings/&lt;/a&gt; Source: Fisheries Statistics Division of the NOAA Fisheries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#using here packages
us_landings &amp;lt;- read_csv(here(&amp;quot;content&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;project&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;DataWrangling&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;data&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;noaa_fisheries.csv&amp;quot;))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Parsed with column specification:
## cols(
##   Year = col_double(),
##   State = col_character(),
##   `AFS Name` = col_character(),
##   `Landings (pounds)` = col_double(),
##   `Dollars (USD)` = col_character()
## )&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go exploring a bit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(us_landings)
View(us_landings)
names(us_landings)
head(us_landings)
tail(us_landings)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data-cleaning-to-get-salmon-landings&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data cleaning to get salmon landings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First: tidying the entire data frame&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;landings_tidy &amp;lt;- us_landings %&amp;gt;% 
  janitor::clean_names() %&amp;gt;% #names to lower case and snake
  mutate(state = str_to_lower(state),#overwrite the state column changing the content to lower case
        afs_name = str_to_lower(afs_name)) %&amp;gt;% #overwrite the afs_name column changing the content to lower case
  mutate(dollars_num = parse_number(dollars_usd))#take only the numbers and create a new column&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, getting just the salmon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;salmon_landings &amp;lt;- landings_tidy %&amp;gt;% 
  mutate(afs_clean = str_remove(afs_name, pattern = &amp;quot;aggregate&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;% #remove string pattern 
  filter(str_detect(afs_clean, pattern = &amp;quot;salmon&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;% 
  separate (afs_clean, into = c(&amp;quot;group&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;species&amp;quot;), sep = &amp;quot;,&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find some grouped summary data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find annual total US landings and dollar value (summing across all states) for each TYPE of salmon using “group_by ()” + “summarize()”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;salmon_summary &amp;lt;- salmon_landings %&amp;gt;% 
  group_by(year, species) %&amp;gt;% 
  summarize(
    tot_landings = sum (landings_pounds),
    tot_value = sum (dollars_num)
  )&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;make-a-graph-of-us-commercial-fisheries-value-by-species-over-time-with-ggplot2&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Make a graph of US commercial fisheries value by species over time with &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;salmon_landings_graph &amp;lt;- ggplot(salmon_summary, aes(x = year, y = tot_landings, group = species)) +
  geom_line(aes(color = species)) +
  theme_bw() +
  labs(x = &amp;quot;year&amp;quot;, y = &amp;quot;US commercial salmon landings (pounds)&amp;quot;)

salmon_landings_graph&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/project/DataWrangling/index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;commercial-fisheries-value-by-state&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2015 commercial fisheries value by state&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s create a finalized table of the top 5 states (by total commercial fisheries value) for 2015 .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;state_value &amp;lt;- landings_tidy %&amp;gt;% 
  filter(year %in% c(2015)) %&amp;gt;% 
  group_by(state) %&amp;gt;% 
  summarize(
    state_value = sum(dollars_num, na.rm = TRUE),
    state_landings = sum(landings_pounds, na.rm = TRUE)
  ) %&amp;gt;% 
  arrange(-state_value) %&amp;gt;% 
  head(5)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;making-a-html-table&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making a HTML table&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we’ll create it as a finalized data frame:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;state_table &amp;lt;- state_value %&amp;gt;% 
  mutate(`Fisheries value ($ millions)` = round(state_value / 1e6, 2),
         `Landings (million pounds)` = round(state_landings / 1e6, 1)) %&amp;gt;% 
  select(-state_value, -state_landings) %&amp;gt;% 
  rename(State = state) %&amp;gt;% 
  mutate(State = str_to_title(State))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, use &lt;code&gt;kable()&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;kableExtra&lt;/code&gt; to nicely format it for HTML:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;kable(state_table) %&amp;gt;% 
  kable_styling(bootstrap_options = &amp;quot;striped&amp;quot;, 
                full_width = FALSE) %&amp;gt;% 
  add_header_above(c(&amp;quot;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;2015 US commercial fisheries - top 5 states by value&amp;quot; = 2))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;table table-striped&#34; style=&#34;width: auto !important; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;border-bottom:hidden&#34; colspan=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;border-bottom:hidden; padding-bottom:0; padding-left:3px;padding-right:3px;text-align: center; &#34; colspan=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;border-bottom: 1px solid #ddd; padding-bottom: 5px; &#34;&gt;
2015 US commercial fisheries - top 5 states by value
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
State
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Fisheries value ($ millions)
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
Landings (million pounds)
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
Alaska
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
1750.20
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
6015.1
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
Maine
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
628.95
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
252.5
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
Massachusetts
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
523.67
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
259.8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
Louisiana
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
369.62
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
1068.5
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
Washington
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
221.54
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
148.8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seagrass meadows under climate change</title>
      <link>/project/seagrass-meadows/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/seagrass-meadows/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Seagrasses are the only flowering plants that are found in the marine environment, covering extensive areas in temperate and tropical coastal areas. Their meadows are among the most valuable ecosystems on Earth. Apart from their cultural services, seagrasses provide key ecological functions for maintaining healthy estuarine and coastal ecosystems. Accordingly, these plants are regarded as a useful indicator of water quality due to their sensitivity to anthropogenic pressures, being highly relevant as one of the biological quality elements required for the assessment of the ecological quality status in coastal and transitional water bodies within the European Water Framework Directive (2000/60/EC). The high ecological importance of their habitats has also promoted their inclusion in the list of Natural habitats of Community interest of the European Habitats Directive (92/43/EEC, Annex I).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, over the last two decades, up to 18% of the world’s documented seagrass area has been lost, with rates of decline accelerating in recent years. This has placed seagrass meadows among the most threatened ecosystems on earth, with loss-rates comparable to those reported for mangroves, coral reefs, and tropical rainforests. These valuable ecosystems and the services they provide are subjected to many pressures, both anthropogenic and natural. Moreover, the present situation of declining seagrasses may be exacerbated by global change drivers. Recent climate change has already impacted marine environments with documented effects on the phenology of organisms, the distributional range of species, and the composition and dynamics of communities. According to the latest IPCC report (AR5), in the coming decades, coastal systems and low-lying areas will increasingly experience adverse climate-related impacts intensified by increasing human-induced pressures. Particularly, the vulnerability of the Basque coast and its marine environment to potential change in present climate regimes is expected to be increased by the demographic pressure, the overexploitation of resources and the high human use of the marine space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within this context habitat suitability models, habitat restoration and habitat classification approaches represent highly promising tools for seagrass conservation. On one hand, through the application of niche models, habitat requirements of the species can be determined and the suitable areas can be estimated under present conditions and projected to future climate scenarios. On the other hand, small-scale transplant experiments of seagrass meadows can provide valuable information for planning major restoration efforts, which might contribute to the improvement of the ecological status in coastal areas. Lastly, extensive and high-resolution habitat maps can support the assessment of the ecosystem status and the influence of natural and anthropogenic impacts over time. Therefore, these tools can provide relevant information not only to implement conservation, restoration and management plans of natural resources, but also to establish adaptation plans to face climate change impacts.
This PhD thesis primarily emerged from the need to conserve Zostera noltii (Hornemann, 1832), although research has also been performed for the semi-annual flexible type of Zostera marina L. Z. noltii is the unique seagrass species occurring in the Basque estuaries which is presently under extinction risk and is found to be highly vulnerable to climate change due to its intertidal distribution. The semi-annual flexible type of Zostera marina L. is an intertidal habitat forming seagrass species that shows a high inter annual variability in extent and location, leading to be particularly vulnerable to local threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-main-stated-objectives-are&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The main stated objectives are:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To explore the applicability of habitat suitability modelling for the conservation of seagrasses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To assess the response of Z. noltii meadows to climate-driven changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To define the best restoration options for Z. noltii meadows in the Basque coast in the basis of field-based experiments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the applicability of hyperspectral airborne imagery to monitor estuarine habitats.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
